Finding Aid for the The Stanley F. Horn Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Stanley F. Horn Collection
2-8-65
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0213
The Stanley F. Horn Collection of Tennessee Manuscripts contains more than six hundred individual pieces. Although they range in date from 1782 to the 1870s, most are concentrated in the first four decades of the nineteenth century. Virtually all of the early governors of Tennessee are represented by one or more documents. There are also papers of Sam Houston, John Sevier, JohnQuincy Adams, James Robertson, Davy Crockett, and others; there is one legal writ bearing the unique signature mark of the “long hunter,” Kasper Mansker.
More than one-third of the items in the Horn Collection are Andrew Jackson papers, making it one of the five foremost corpora of Jackson material in existence. There are letters between the Tennessee soldier-statesman and such contemporaries as Col. Samuel Swartwout, William H. Crawford, Joseph Anderson. Hugh Lawson White, and Willie Blount. There is an interesting and useful score of documents written late in 1814. requisitioning equipment and rations for the Battle of New Orleans.
Other important groups of papers comprised by the Horn Collection include:
Letters of William Blount about Indian affairs
Documents concerning the Aaron Burr conspiracy
Letters of James Winchester from Cragfont
Papers pertaining to Tennessee land grants
In addition, the Collection also includes some substantive letters on Civil War matters.
The Special Collections Department of the Joint University Libraries, Nashville, acquired this Collection of Tennessee Manuscripts in 1964 through the generosity of Mr. Stanley F. Horn. They are preserved in its Treasure Room.
Scope and Contents
This collection, containing approximately 650 items for the dates 1780-1905, is composed of accounts, applications, appointments, bonds, contracts, correspondence, court records, depositions, land records, estate records, Burr conspiracy data, military records, letters and papers of Andrew Jackson, Andrew Jackson III, Daniel Montgomery, and a few papers of John Overton. The papers of Andrew Jackson make up the largest portion of the collection. There are twenty-five letters written by Jackson between the dates 1813-1845, four of which are published in Bassett, Approximately one hundred and ten letters in the collection were written to Andrew Jackson and about one hundred additional letters are for the Jackson period. There are about forty letters which Tall in the period of the Civil War and twenty others in the latter part of the nineteenth century. The subjects dealt with in the Jackson period include items about the Creek Indian War; military supplies; Indian lands; the presidential elections of 1824, 1828, 1832, 1836, 1840, and 1844; Jackson’s political observations; Adams and Clay Junto; Burr conspiracy; Sam Houston and the Texas question; Jacksonfs military exploits; removal of the Indians west of the Mississippi; the Whigs; James Knox Polk; Martin Van Buren; Jackson and the tariff; nullification proclamation; Muscle Shoals as a possible arsenal; John C. Calhoun’s opinion of Jackson; William H. Crawford’s opinion of Jackson; and other phases of Jackson’s career.
The most important correspondents for this period are Joseph Anderson, R. Armstrong, Francis P. Blair, William Blount, V/illie Blount, John Brown, Neil S. Brown, Rouks Butler, John Catron, John H. Dew, Samuel Dixon, John H. Katon, A. Edwards, A. H. Everett, James Gadsden, John P. Helfenstein, Cave Johnson, S. Hm Laughlin, Eben A. Lester, R. Riker, James Robertson, V/. P. Rowles, J. F. Schermerhorn, John Sevier, James Ross Snowden, Samuel Swartwout, Walker Tandy, R. B. Taney, James G. Taylor, Hugh Lawson White, and James Winchester.
The most important correspondents for the Civil War period are William G. Brownlow, A. S. Colyar, E. A. Flewellen, Isham G. Harris, Andrew Jackson III, Samuel Milligan, and David T. Patterson.
The papers of Andrew Jackson III contain correspondence during the Civil War with his aunts, his ’toother, Sarah lorke Jackson, and his father, Andrew Jackson, Jr. A small diary kept by Andrew Jackson III in 1863 contains a few entries about troop movements.] There is a “Report of Heavy Batteries, Vicksburg, Mississippi” dated October, 1862, which commends Colonel Jackson for his “gallantry and unceasing vigilance during the siege”.
The Daniel Montgomery Papers for the period 1795-1852 are primarily land grants, deeds, indentures, surveys, and other legal documents for Sumner County. The papers contain a small amount of correspondence for the period 1815-1848.
The remainder of fthe Collection is composed of clippings, correspondence about gifts and invitations, memorials, recommendations, resolutions, and a few military records for the period 1795-1815.
- Applications and Recommendations, 1829-1832 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Church and Bible Items, 1825-1848 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Clippings - Advertisements, etc., 1841-1853 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings - William Carroll & Legislative Acts (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings - Confederate Items, 1862, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Clippings - Confederate Poems (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Clippings - Obituaries - Carels and Meserve (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Donelson, Andrew Jackson - Pamphlet by Allen Hall (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Legal Documents - Agreements, 1798-1859 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Legal Documents - Appointments, 1812-1832 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Legal Documents - Bonds, 1781-1836 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Legal Documents - Court Records, 1782-1843 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Legal Documents - Declaration of Independence (Facs) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Legal Documents - Depositions, 1791-1821 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Legal Documents - Land Records: Indentures, Grants, etc. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Legal Documents - Legislative Acts, 1815, 1838, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Legal Documents - Miscellaneous - Estates, etc. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Legal Documents - Steamboat License, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Miscellaneous Articles - Re: Lawyer and Distilling (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Miscellaneous - Memoranda (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Remonstrance of Robert Hays to the General Assembly (Box 1, Folder 21)
- School Records: Cumberland College - Petition to change its name (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1780-1860; 1905
  - Adams - Bainbridge (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Barbour-Bell (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Blount, William (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Blount, Willie - Brown, Neil S. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Caffery - Combs (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Davidson - Ewing (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fain-Hobbs (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Johnson - Livingston (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - March-McKean (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Montgomery, C.T. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Nance - Robertson (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Royall, Anne (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sevier - Taylor (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Walker - Winchester (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Civil War Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1869-1905 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Burr Conspiracy - Correspondence, 1828-1829 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Burr Conspiracy - Manuscripts of newspaper items, 1806 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Burr Conspiracy - Pamphlet United States Telegraph, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Burr Conspiracy - Pamphlet, United States Telegraph, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Andrew Jackson III Papers - Correspondence, 1845-1865 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Andrew Jackson III Papers - Correspondence, 1864-1866 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Andrew Jackson III Papers - Correspondence, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Andrew Jackson III Papers - Correspondence, 1862-1865 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Andrew Jackson III Papers - Diary Order, Report, and Telegram (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Samuel Jackson - Commission, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Daniel Montgomery Papers - Accounts Bills, Notes, Receipts, 1817-1854 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Daniel Montgomery Papers - Correspondence, 1815-1848 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Daniel Montgomery Papers - Legal Documents, 1835-1852 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Daniel Montgomery Papers - Summer County Land Grants, Indentures, etc., 1795-1831 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Overton Papers - Documents - Re: Land and Taxes, 1805, etc.jLetter of James A. Chandler, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Andrew Jackson Correspondence
  - Incoming - Unsigned letters, 1829-1841 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Incoming - Anderson-Blair, 1837-1841 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Incoming - Blount, Willie-Butler, 1811-1845 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Incoming - “C'S”, 1796-1841 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Incoming - “D’s”, 1820-1844 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Incoming - “E’s”, 1833-1844 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Incoming - “G’s”, 1829-1844 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Incoming - “H’S”, 1828-1844 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Incoming - “J’s” and “K’s”, 1829-1844 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Incoming - “L’s” and “M’s”, 1832-1844 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Incoming - “N’s”, “O’s”, and “P’s”, 1829-1834 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Incoming - “R’s”, 1825-1844 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Incoming - “S’s”, 1825-1844 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Incoming - “T’s”, 1831-1844 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Incoming - “V’s”, “W’s”, and “Y’s”, 1821-1844 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Outgoing, 1813-1816 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Outgoing, 1818-1824 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Outgoing, 1825-1828 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Outgoing, 1829-1845 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Andrew Jackson Papers
  - Accounts, Bills, Notes, Receipts, etc., 1797-1861 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Clippings - “Arbuthnot and Ambrister,” National Intelligencer, 1818 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Clippings - Andrew Jackson and the War of 1812, ETC. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Re: Congratulations, Memorials, Recommendations, and Resolutions, 1829-1845 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Re: Gifts, 1829-1332 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Re: Invitations, 1807-1845 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Re: Pedigreed Animals, Henry Cotten, 1826-1837 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Military Records - Accounts, 1795-1836 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Military Records - melica1 Records, 1813-1815 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Military Records - Military Supplies, Re: Clothing, Horses, Munitions, and Rations, 1797-1815 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Military Records - Morning Reports and Miscellaneous Records, 1813-1814 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Andrew Jackson Correspondence Outgoing 1813-1845
  - To Richard Call, Undated
  - To David Holmes, Governor of Mississippi Territory, 1813, March 16
  - Re: Creek Indian Chief, 1814, August 10
  - To William H. Crawford, 1816, October 18
  - To Secretary of War, 1816, November 12
  - To Samuel Swartwout, 1823, December 16
  - To Samuel Swartwout Bassett, Volume III, pages 33-34, 1824, March 4
  - To Samuel Swartwout, 1824 September 27
  - To Samuel Swartwout - Bassett, Volume III, pages 268-69, 1824, December 14
  - To John Quincy Adams, 1824, December 25
  - To Samuel Swartwout - Bassett, Volume III, pages 278-80, 1825, February 22
  - To Samuel Swartwout - Incomplete in Bassett, Volume III, pages 284-85, 1825, May 16
  - To Major H. Lee, 1827, December 1
  - To Governor James B. Ray, 1828, Februaiy 23
  - To James Ronaldson, 1828, January 4
  - To Committee declining invitation, 1829, October 2
  - To William W. Gray, Thank you note, 1831, May 2
  - Unsigned letter to Gentlemen, 1831, December 29
  - To Sarah Yorke Jackson, 1834, May 19
  - To Major N. Clark - Letter of Introduction, 1835, May 25
  - To Committee declining invitation, 1837, April 1
  - To James Johnson, 1840, October 5
  - To John H. Wheeler, Raleigh, North Carolina, 1842, December 21
  - To Commodore J. D. Elliott, United States Navy, declining offer of royal sarcophagus - Bassett, Volume VI, pages 391-92, 1845, March 27
Name Index
This is a name index of the correspondents in the Stanley Horn Collection, together with the dates of the letters. The figures in parentheses immediately following the name denote the number of letters, if more than one. The last number listed refers to the box in which the material is to be found. The letters in box four were all written to Andrew Jackson or by him.
Acklen, J. Hayes, (3), 1877-1878, 2
Adams, John Quincy, 1824, 2
Anderson, Joseph, undated, 4, Re: W. H. Crawford’s opinion of Jackson in the Seminole War
Armstrong, R., (2), undated, 4, Re: Politics
Babb, A., 1827, 2
Bailey, R., 1831, 2
Bainbridge, A., 1846, 2
Barbour, J. S., 1829, 2
Barry, W. T., 1832, 2
Bass, J. M., (3), 1839, 1845, 2
Beauchamp, M., 1841, 4
Bell, John, 1841, 2
Blackie, G. S., 1863, 2
Blair, Francis P., 1837, 4, Re: Van Buren and Jackson’s Washington friends
Blount, William, (12), 1794-1796, 2, Re: Payment of troops
Blount, Willie, (6), 1811-1835, 2, Uf Re: Removal of Indians; opening of Mississippi to Hew Orleans; Van Puren, Judge Hugh l.awson White
Bolton, W. C., 1845, 4
Breathett, John, 1828, JU, Re: Presidential election of 1826
Brcnan, Thomas H., 1829, 4, Re: Horses
Bronauph, Rebecca, 1824, 4
r Brown, John, 1813, 2
Brown, John C, (2), 1878-1889, 2
Brown, NeillS., 1853, 2
Brownlow, W. G., (2), 1862, 1866, 2, Re: Mistreatment during Civil War; success of Radicals in Illinois, Indiana, Ohio, West and Northwest
Butler, Anthony, 1811, 4
Butler, Rouks, 1827, 4, Re: Accounts of Jackson’s military exploits; slanders about Mrs. Jackson
Caffery, D., 1835, 2
Carels, Joseph S., 1905, 2
Carmack, E. W., undated, 2
Carter, E. B., 1841, 2
Cass, Lewis, 1831, 2
Catron, John, 1837, 1864, 2, 4, Re: Politics-John Bell, William Carroll, Felix Grundy, Felix Robertson and Judge White
Chandler, James A., 1826, 3
Cheatham, L. P., 1841, 4
Claiborne, William C. C, 1796, 4
Cocke, J., 1821, 2
Cocke, J., 1821, 2
Claiborne, William C. C, 1796, 4
Cocke, J., 1821, 2
Coffee, John, 1828, 3
Cole, John, 1844, 4
Coleman, Blacknan, 1830, 4
Colyar, A. S., 1877, 2, Re: Terms offered by Hampton Roads Commission
Combs, L., 1858, 2
Cotten, Henry, 1826, 5, Re: Horses
Cushman, John W., 1829, 4
Davidson, William, 1780, 2
Desha, Rob, 1830, 4
Dew, John H., 1837, 4, Re: Politics--Robert M. Burton, John Hall, James Knox Polk and the Whigs
Dixon, Samuel, 184U, h, Re: Politics and Indian fighting
Donelson, Andrew Jackson, (3), 1820-1841, 4
Donelson, E. Y., (6), 1864-1866, 3
Donelson, Elizabeth, 1845, 2, Re: Andrew Jackson’s death; arrival of Houston
Douglass, William, 1828, 4, Re: Political gathering
Dupuy, Charles M., 1832, 4
Duryee, Richard, 1834, 4
Eads, James D., 1840, 4
Eaton, John H., (2), 1831, 1843, 2
Edwards, A., 1844, 4, Re: Nomination of James K. Polk
Essex R., 1833, 4
Everett, A. H., 1824, 2
Ewing, Andrew, 1853, 2
Fain, N., 1831, 2
Flewellen, E. A., 1863, 2, Re: Inability of Confederate medical officers to meet emergencies
Foster, Ephraim, H., 1840, 2, Re: Death of Hugh Lawson White
Fowler, Joseph S., 1869, 2
Franklin, B. J., 1854, 2
Franklin, James, 1822, 2
Frith,.W., 1829, 3
Gadsden, James, (4), 1816, 1844, 2, 4, Re: Politics--Texas, Mexico, Sam Houston and James K. Polk
Gardner, James, 1833, 4
Gealiot, C, 1834, 4
Gibson, Alexander, 1831, 4
Goodlett, A. G., 1848, 2
Gordon, Martin, 1829, 4
Greer, A., 1832, 4
Guinn, Samuel, 1832, 4
Harris, Isham G., 1861, 2, Re: Permission for Arkansas to install battery on Island No. 10
Hays, S. D., 1814, 2
Helfenstein, John P., 1828, 4, Re: John Quincy Adams and Henry Clay
Higgins, Hiram H., 1826, 2
Hill, H. R. W., 1834, 2
Hill, Henry, Jr., 1840, 4
Hobbs, Edward D., 1814, 2
Holland, Elijah, 184O, 4
Houston, Samuel, 1846, 2
Hubbard, David, 1844, 4
Hunton, William E., 1829, 4
Jack, C. J., 1829, 4
Jackson, Andrew (25), 1813-1845, 4
Jackson, Andrew Jr., 1864, 3
Jackson, Andrew III, (4), 1864-1865, 3
Jackson, Sarah Yorke, (8), 1862-1865, 3
Janney, Sam M., 1829, 5
Johnson, Cave, (2), 1835, 1866, 2
Johnson, John, 1829, 4
Jones, W. M., 1844, 4
Keaton, O. W., 1830’s, 4
Kellog, Miner K., 1832, 4
King, William R., 1832, 4
Knox, Henry, 1794, 2
Laughlin, H. H., 1844, 4, Re: Poljtics and Texas
Lea, John M., undated fragment, 2
Lea, Luke, 1834, 2
Leonard, L., 1840, 4, Re: Politics
Lester, Eben A., 1833, 2, Re: Nullification proclamation
Lewis, W. B., 1844, 4
Lindsley, A. V. S., 1864, 2
Livingston, Edward, undated, 2
Lytle, Robert, 1834, 4
Mabry, J., 1828, 3
Manning, Richard J., 1836, 4
Martin, E. L., 1834, 4
Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1860, 2
McCammon, Samuel, 1857, 2
McKenry, Robert, 1832, 4
McKean, Maria P., 1814, 2
McLane, Louis, 1833, 4
Mey, James G., 1812, 4
Milligan, Samuel, 1864, 2
Montgomery, C. T., (8), 1829, 2
Montgomery, Daniel, 1838, 3
Moore, James M., 1833, 4
Nance, W. L., 1853, 2
Neville, Morgan, 1834, 4
Ogle, Alexander, 1830, 4
Owen, John, 1829, 4
Parks, John, 1828, 3
Patterson, C. H., 1865, 2
Patterson, David T., 1864, 2, Re: Military authorities in Nashville - Confident of ability to defeat Hood
Patterson, Will H., 1865, 2
Patton, Benjamin, 1830, 4
Phillips, Benjamin, 1831, 4
Phillips, Isaac, 1833, 4
Pitcher, Nathaniel, 182, 4
Poinsett, J. R., 1834, 4
Porter, James D., undated ca 1875, 2
Putnam, Julia, 1865, 3
Ragan, John, 1825, 4
Ramsey, Charles R., 1834, 4
Randal, Roswell, 1836, 2
Ready, Charles, 1857, 2
Rees, Thad B., 1840, 2, Re: Politics
Rhea, John, 1812, 2
Rickard, William, (2), 1797, 1800, 2, Re: Death of George Washington
Riker, R., 1834, 2, Re: Politics and the presidential election
Roberts, L. P., 1838, 4, Re: Judge White’s influence in Knoxville
Robertson, Felix, 1828, 3
Robertson, James, 1797, 2, Re: Indian affairs
Robertson, Wyndham, 1844, 4, Re: Altercation between James K. Polk and Henry A. Wise
Robinson, William, 1830, 4
Rowles, W. P., 1842, Re: Henry Clay, tariff, and bank
Royall, Anne, (3), 1824-1838, 2
Saltonstall, Roswell, 1833, 4
Savary, Charley, 1840, 4
Schermerhorn, J. F., 1827, 4, Re: Political forces at work against Jackson
Sevier, John, (3), 1797, 1799, 1809, 2, Re: Indian lands and Indian treaties
Sevier,.Washington, 1800, 2
Shakers, The, 1833, 4
Shein, James G., 1825, 4
Simpson, S., 1829, 4
Slaughter, Thomas S., 1829, 4
Smith, Policy, 1832, 2
Snowden, James Ross, 1844, 4
Sommerville, John H., 1832, 4, Re: Indian lands
Staatz, Cuyler, 1828, 4, Re; Esteem for Jackson
Standifer, James, 1816, 4
Stewart, G. H., 1833, 4
Stewart, James, 1830, 4
Stinson, A. P., 1844, 4
Storm, Stephen, 1850, 2, Re: Travel and customs in Tennessee; everyone rides horseback
Swartwout, Samuel, (2), 1825, 1831, 4, Re: Henry Clay’s opposition to Jackson
Taney, R. B., 1844, 4, Re: James K. Polk, Martin Van Buren and the bank
Taylor, H. W., 1839, 4
Taylor, James, (2), 1831, 2, 4
Taylor, James G., 1844, 4, Re: Qualifications of James K. Polk and Martin Van Buren
Thomason, Edward, 1833, 4
Totten, H. S. G., 1844, 4
Turner, M. W., 1815, 3
Van Eyck, A., 1844, 4
Walker, Tandy, 1858, 2, Re: Acts of the Choctaw Nation and requests copy of Tennessee Laws
Wayne, Antony, 1854, 2
White, Hugh, 1862, 2
White, Hugh Lawson, (5), 1821-1836, 2, 4, Re: Politics
White, Maunsel, 1833, 4, Re: Jackson’s proclamation
Whiteley, R. H. R., 1863, 2, Re: Military supplies
Wickliffe, Charles A., 1814, 2
Williams, John, 1818, 2
Williamson, John, 1828, 3
Wilson, Nathaniel, 1844, 5
Winant, B. P., 1844, 4
Winchester, James, (8), 1797-1812, 2, Re: Indian troubles and military matters
Winchester, Judge James, 1801, 2
Witherell, Sarah, undated, 3
Woodbury, Levi, 1833, 4, Re: Judge Wayne’s choice as President of Convention in Georgia
Wool, John E. 1834, 4, Re: Military expenses
Yandell, D. W., undated, 2, Re: Surgeon Stout
Yell, A., 1836, 4